<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Digital Publishing for Digital Humans]]></title><description><![CDATA[Thoughts about how people in digital humanities/history/journalism can better collaborate and share knowledge]]></description><link>https://joshuarrrr.github.io/hubpress.io</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 16:01:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://joshuarrrr.github.io/hubpress.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Portfolio Sites for Non-coding Journalists]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Creating personal or portfolio websites shouldn&#8217;t really be that hard. And for people who work with web technology daily, it isn&#8217;t, because we&#8217;re surrounded by a proliferation of tools that make it easy for developers to create and launch simple sites. After all, most personal sites are not that complex: A list of clips, a brief description of the person, a resume or CV, and maybe a blog. Just pick your favorite static site generator (jekyll [js], hexo [js], hugo [go], or pelican [python] are all fine, depending on your language of choice) and choose a place to host the site (GitHub Pages or Amazon S3 are good free options), and you can have your own digital space up and running in no time.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But as good as these tools, are, they generally assume a good deal of implicit technical knowledge that can seem mysterious and daunting for anyone who doesn&#8217;t already do development work. So journalists, designers, and academics often turn to easier options like Wordpress, Squarespace, or Weebly, instead. All of these require no technical experience to get started, and provide lots of themes that seem to work well out of the box.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The problem is that these are wildly bloated for the purpose of simply updating and maintaining a couple of web pages. While it&#8217;s possible to set up a very simple personal site, these products are much more focused on more complicated corporate sites, e-commerce sites, or high-volume blogging. Further bloat comes from installing numerous plugins and themes, which also must support many possible use cases. The result is often a slow, expensive site, which requires constant updates.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Some of the digital journalists that I highly respect and look up to (<a href="https://medium.com/learning-journalism-tech/github-makes-portfolio-sites-for-journalists-cheap-and-kinda-easy-bd53d882185f#.a8wzcafdc">Tyler Fisher</a> and <a href="http://lenagroeger.s3.amazonaws.com/makeawebsite/makeawebsite.html">Lena Groeger</a>) have tried to bridge the gap by writing detailed tutorials about setting up personal sites using GitHub Pages. But I think it&#8217;s important to acknowledge and separate the two very different goals that may go into building a personal site. The first is the practical goal of just getting a site up and the ability to easily edit and change its content. The second goal, with more long-term benefits, is to learn: about digital publishing, web technologies, version control, etc. Most of these tutorials assume an audience that is interested in both goals. But in reality, launching a static site, especially for a novice, puts the focus much more heavily on the learning objective.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The list of topics to be learned by the unitiated is substantial:</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>Plain text files and plain text editor</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bash and the command line</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Markdown syntax</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Git, GitHub, how they&#8217;re different and the concept of version control</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Plain text config files</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>HTML basics</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>CSS syntax</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Manual image editing and management</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>]]></description><link>https://joshuarrrr.github.io/hubpress.io/2017/01/18/Portfolio-Sites-for-Non-coding-Journalists.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://joshuarrrr.github.io/hubpress.io/2017/01/18/Portfolio-Sites-for-Non-coding-Journalists.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Digital publishing]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>